This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
For Software Engineering Radio, this is
Robert Blumen. I have with me today
Jeroen Mulder. He is an enterprise and
security architect with over 25 years in
IT and cloud technology. He's held a
number of roles in IT companies
including Atos and Origin. Until 2021,
he was head of applications and
multi-cloud services for Fujitsu in the
Netherlands.
Jeroen is the author of the book
Multi-Cloud Architecture and Governance
and we will be discussing a range of
topics in the area of multi-cloud and
hybrid cloud. Jeroen, welcome to
Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you very much and compliments for
pronouncing my name for being a Dutch.
I do my best.
We do have listeners in over 100
countries so we are often dealing with
people's names from all over the world.
Yeah.
Before we talk about multi-cloud, could
you give us a brief overview of cloud
computing including the idea of private
cloud and public cloud?
Yeah, that's already a good start for a
debate since what is multi-cloud? In my
world, it's a mix, hybrid cloud, private
cloud, public cloud, etc. So, what I
usually what I try to do in my books is
to give a definition and at least to
give something to work with. So,
multi-cloud would involve at least two
clouds basically and whether that is a
private cloud sitting on VMware or
anything in combination with a public
cloud, whether that's going to be
Microsoft Azure, AWS or whatsoever or
that we have a combination of two public
clouds. That's all multi-cloud to me.
The real trick in multi-cloud is whether
you use it as a multi-cloud because I
can have stuff running in Azure and I
can have stuff running in AWS. If these,
let's say these environments are not
connected, and then I'm just using two
separate clouds.
If they are connected as an environment,
then I'm going to talk about
multi-cloud. And that use it typically
within the enterprise that I work with
so far, we have private cloud stacks
sitting in on-premises data centers but
mostly or in co-locations, and then
stretching into public clouds for
whatever usage. That can be a disaster
recovery solution in public cloud or
development being done in public clouds.
And after all, because for instance,
because of compliancy rules or
whatsoever, have the production on
private clouds. So, that's a little bit
of a definition that we use. And having
said that, I know that a lot of my
colleagues and other experts may have
different definitions. There is even an
an official definition by Gartner, which
is all true. Basically, I don't think
that that is just one definition.
Multi-cloud, basically, if you just
strip down the word multi-cloud, it's
two two clouds as a minimum. That's
multi. And I'm using at least two
clouds. And that can be anything in my
world. With hybrid cloud, it's a little
bit different. That's more specific.
That's private combination with public
cloud where the private cloud sits in an
on-premises data center.
So, that's a start. But it's already a
good start to have a fierce debate on
what is it actually. And then, if we
really want to go down the rabbit hole,
it is AWS, it's Azure, it's Oracle
Cloud, it's Google Cloud, it's
everything that comes with it. There's
so much choice for that matter and what
you can use. And that's where the real
thing starts. What do I use? What do I
want to achieve? Where do I want to use
it for? That's where the real
interesting stuff starts, as far as I am
concerned.
So, you raised a ton of points that
we'll probably spend the rest of the
hour discussing. I want to delve a
little bit into this idea of private
cloud. When cloud computing started, we
had public cloud, and then we had stuff
in people's on-prem data centers. We
wouldn't have called that private cloud.
It's just
how we always did things. So, what makes
something a private cloud versus a bunch
of computers that the enterprise owns?
Awfully good question. When I started
off in this job, a private cloud was At
first, we called it utility computing.
It was basic And if you really look at
it at its core, the big mainframes where
you ran multiple applications or
multiple environments on top of,
basically that was already the
predecessor of a private cloud. A
private cloud is a hardware stack, and
I'm running uh multiple applications or
databases, whatsoever, on top of that
hardware stack. Is that cloud or is that
utility computing? Basically, I'm not
running an application. It's not a
one-to-one relationship between the
application server. It's an N-to-one.
So, I can have different departments,
different developer groups, whatsoever,
running on the same server with
applications, etc. Okay, so if you want
to call that a private cloud, I'm cool
with that. That starts with the
virtualization of the whole thing.
That's where you actually got the
possibility to chop your server into
multiple servers, or at least have it
pretend that it was multiple servers.
Yeah, you can call it a private cloud if
you want. I'm not strict in for that
matter in using the word private cloud
for that. As I said, we started off
using the word utility computing because
because more departments or more
developer groups were using the same
server. It's all good to me. It's not
like
Let's say the theory underneath it is
that you share components underneath the
infrastructure. So, the network
components or the storage or whatsoever.
That's what basically defines the cloud
definition and that's something that in
public cloud has extended to that really
scaled out and in private cloud you
could scale in private cloud obviously
but not the way that you would do it in
Azure or in AWS or any public cloud.
So we can argue about what is or is not
cloud but I see a couple of
characteristics of public cloud
computing which is self-service, API
driven, decentralized.
Is that being adopted as a model for
on-prem and privately owned computing so
that everybody can deal with every
compute resource more or less the same
way?
Yeah, I would say that that's a good
definition. Still
the real definition is in the shared
components and if you allow people to
work on let's call it the same system
and enter it with an API or whatsoever.
Yeah, you could define it as a cloud. I
love these t-shirts that says cloud is
just someone else's computer which is
basically the sole and one and only
truth. It's basically someone else's
computer that you're working on.
And you do that with an API, you get
into that using an API. If that's the
definition of a cloud, yeah, then a
private stack that I'm entering with an
API as a developer and I'm using the
stack, I'm using the hardware, the
servers and the shared components, the
storage, the network, etc. That's
basically what cloud is about. And
that's not different, not really that
much different from how the public
clouds work. Let's not overcomplicate
things and the public cloud is nothing
more, nothing less than indeed someone
else's computer. There are two main
differences. First one is scalability.
It is scalability is scalable to
whatever, almost endlessly which is also
not completely true by the way. And the
second thing might be the fact that all
these public clouds really, yeah, offer
you services that make your life a
little bit more easier than it was let's
say 20 30 years ago. So those were I
would say that these are the two main
differences with a private cloud.
With a private cloud, you will still
have the service sitting somewhere on
somewhere on the floor. You will still
have racks with network equipment. You
will still have racks with storage
equipment. Someone has to deal with that
and that's again not different from
public clouds. There are engineers for
Microsoft or Amazon or whoever that have
to deal with the physical hardware
that's sitting somewhere. It's I always
loved I already mentioned that in that
t-shirt. I have this one customer. I'm
not going to call out names that was
really absolutely fanatic, really
enthusiastic about oh, that serverless
concept. That's something that I really
want to try out. And then when I started
asking, why would you really want to go
into serverless? If you have a use case,
a really good use case for serverless,
go there. Absolutely. It's pay as you
go. It's a fantastic technology. But
don't think that serverless means that
there are no servers involved, which is
a completely different thing. It's not
really cloud basically. And it still
strikes me every now and then how many
customers not IT guys because IT guys
basically know let's say managers,
C-level guys really think oh, cloud is
something magical. It's not. It's
technology. Come on. It is not magic.
We've had now 20 years of cloud
computing. In the early days, you
wouldn't have thought of running your
entire workload on the cloud. Today, if
you're a startup, you wouldn't think of
running it yourself. 20 years is longer
than the lifespan of most software. So
for a first order, we could say that
everything that's running anywhere now
had the option of being run either on
the cloud or on prem and companies have
decided where they want their workload
to be, how are companies making that
decision now of if they want to run
their own workload or let someone else
run it?
Yeah, really good question. We see a lot
of difference between various
industries. I work with customers,
enterprises, large enterprises that
really want to get rid of their data
centers. They don't want to manage that
anymore. And also because of something
that I call the voice of the customer.
Customers are demanding new application,
new features of applications all the
time and in even an increasingly faster
way.
Those industries that have to deal with
that type of customers are really
looking into going into public cloud
because it's way more flexible and agile
than their on-premises data centers.
And then we have industries like
healthcare, financial institutions even,
that are still reluctant. Not all of
them, but quite a number of them,
especially in Europe where I am, with
large banks, they are still quite
reluctant to get their most critical
systems into cloud. They want to have
it, let's say, tangible in their own
data centers, have it really under their
own control and not putting their
control in the hands of a public
provider.
And one of the other things that is
really then an argument against using
public clouds is the fact that most
public clouds are American companies,
which is a constraint for a lot of
European enterprises. So, are we
trusting an American company to work
with our data? Basically, because we're
putting the data on their
infrastructure.
So, there are a number of arguments and
there's a lot of compliance and rules
and and stuff that you need to take into
account before you start actually moving
your environments into cloud.
Having said that, we absolutely see a
shift going on and that's not because
of, let's say, the financial component
of cloud because
that's always one of the first, well,
questions or reasons that companies like
ourselves, yeah, we want to go into
cloud because we think we have an idea
that it might be cheaper. We go like,
"No. If that's your sole reason to go
into cloud, don't go there because it's
not going to be cheaper in first.
It might be at some point, but please
work out your business case really
carefully because it's not like if I get
my stuff as it is and I'll simply
transition it to the cloud that I'm
better off in a financial way of
speaking. It's not going to work like
that. If you go like, "But my
customers," and that includes banking
because just look at my phone, I do
everything in terms of banking, I do it
on my phone right now. So, even
financial institutions, health care,
same thing. I have my health care apps
on my phone right now.
So, they are thinking of moving into
cloud. They also have to deal with the
voice of the customer because we as a
customer, we want new features, we want
new applications, we want everything as
easy as it can be. And typically, well,
preferably, I need to say, with just one
click on a phone. Just that we can keep
it with us all the time. That means that
they have to start thinking about
developing new applications, new
features, new code, and even in a speedy
way.
The only way to do that, well, may maybe
not the only way, but the fastest way to
do that is by using the cloud services.
So, yeah, there's a shift, absolutely a
shift going on right now. Is it going
fast enough or I'm not exactly sure. We
see a shift, but we also see that there
are still large enterprises that are
holding on to their own data centers,
let's put it that way. So, it's still a
long way to go.
You mentioned the idea of
data governance where firms for
compliance reasons may
want to maintain tighter control over
the assets where the data lives.
I'm also aware of regulations such as
GDPR in Europe that require data
locality, which I think could go either
way because the enterprise may or may
not have a data center in the country
where they want to operate. Like you to
expand on that a bit and also take into
account compute locality where to what
extent do cloud providers offer a value
proposition of they can put their
compute closer to where the business is
customers are without the business
having to construct the new data center
somewhere where they want to have
business.
Yeah, there are a couple of ways to look
at that. First of all, it's about laws
and regulations and being able to move
within these laws and regulations
including GDPR and all the variants that
we have in European countries, which are
basically variants under GDPR
regulations.
There are differences between the
countries. Some countries are really
strict and where the data should be and
other countries are a little bit more,
let's say, flexible, do allow a little
bit more.
And it also depends on what sort of data
that you're keeping. If that's really
privacy-sensitive data, then it's
already a completely different debate
than, let's say, generic data that could
be found anywhere on the internet.
And then there is indeed the debate,
okay, so where are the data centers? I
live in the Netherlands. We have Azure
data centers over here. Azure is mostly
seen as a trusted company to put your
data on because the data centers are in
the Amsterdam region.
There are also there we have some debate
on, okay, but the data centers are
regulated, are owned by an American
company. So, are we still okay then to
put our data into those data centers
even though they are within, let's say,
the country borders?
So, I would say that the Netherlands is
a typically, I'm almost afraid to say
so, but I can really prove it, it really
is an Azure country. Most companies use
Azure as a public cloud in this country.
In other countries where AWS has data
centers, it might be completely the
other way around.
And that I'm not saying that AWS is not
used in Netherlands. On the contrary, I
work for a company called Philips. Their
health suite is built on AWS all the
way. So, it is used.
I think that the real debate should be,
okay, so what would be the best
offering, the best services that a cloud
has or a cloud provider can offer us in
terms of what we really need to fulfill
customer requirements.
And obviously, yes, data and where the
data resides, where the data is is
stored, obviously, that is important. We
have strong regulations, we have strong
laws and rules and compliance rules and
everything that ensure that your data is
kept in a proper way and is stored in a
proper way. Also with encryption
technologies and identity and access
management, especially access
management.
That's It's not just where the data is,
it's also who can access the data. And
that's something that you control
yourself. That's not something that
Sure, there are laws for that, but it's
also something that you as a company, as
an administrator or a developer can
control largely by yourselves by
defining the roles, access to the roles,
who may access the data, when, where,
why. That is on top of where the data
actually sits, which is I sometimes have
the feeling that these two debates are
mixed or mingled with each other. But it
is absolutely a debate, absolutely.
So, you brought up something and I I
want to come back to this of how a
company can manage identity and access
management in a multi-cloud environment.
So, let's put a pin in that. We've been
talking more about what these different
clouds are and the reasons, the business
case for being on one or another. Now,
to get more into the title of the
conversation we're having, multi-cloud,
do most companies then pick one single
cloud vendor, or do most companies have
a relationship with multiple cloud
vendors for different reasons?
Again, both happen. The enterprise that
I work with typically have chosen one
cloud provider that is sort of their
primary cloud. That can be a an
on-premise or I would say that a private
stack. So, we still have a lot of
enterprises that have huge VMware stacks
in their own data centers.
Got nothing against that, on the
contrary. And if a company chooses to go
into public cloud, then we typically see
that they choose one of the bigger
clouds.
It's mostly with the multinationals, and
especially with the multinationals that
also have presence in, for instance,
Asian countries, and especially in
China,
that they need to go to a second cloud,
whether that's going to be Alibaba Cloud
or Tencent in China, or what sort
because of the latency, because of
compliancy, obviously. There are a lot
of reasons why they have to have a
second cloud.
In Europe, I do see companies that have
multiple clouds, public clouds, they use
multiple clouds,
but then it's really a matter of the use
case. Typically, use case that I see is
that really data-intensive companies
tend to look at Google Cloud just for
the data.
But if you look at, let's say, the more
common services that they would also use
in their own premises and their own
on-premises data centers,
they would look at more at Azure. And
then we have the typical cloud native,
and I hope I'm not offending anyone, the
the typically cloud native companies or
that are really already moving up to
more cloud native are using more and
more AWS. And that's because that's just
my take on it, it's just my perception,
my interpretation, if you want, is that
AWS is more like building blocks that
you really can play with as a developer
where Microsoft Azure is built really
from a services standpoint of view. If I
look at myself, I find it easier to work
with Azure than with AWS, but I can do
stuff in AWS that I really go like,
"Okay, so I can see why a developer
would be completely thrilled by having
these options in a public cloud for
development." So, it's really depending
on the use cases, I would say.
You raised uh few points and I'm making
some notes, so I hope that I can get
back to all of these things without
forgetting anything.
So, one thing I want to come back to is
the idea between there's a lowest common
denominator of what all the cloud
providers have, which is VMs,
Mhm.
load balancers, VPCs, maybe blob
storage. So, if you're the multinational
and you're thinking we need to run
workloads on the best cloud provider in
Asia, Europe, US, might be a different
answer, so you're going to stick with
the lowest common denominator versus
somebody picking the best cloud based on
differentiated services where Google's
better at data,
AWS is better at cloud native. So, do
you see the competition as it being more
driven by locality and doing the most
reliable job at the same things everyone
else does or companies trying to
differentiate themselves as saying, "We
are better at this and you should do
this thing on us?"
Ooh.
Let's start by saying that a lot of
enterprises are still really working on
VM level. So, basically, it's just the
way that they you were used to work in
their own on-premises data center,
virtual machines. That's what they
understood, and that's what they used to
in terms of infrastructure.
We also see the two big shifts that are
happening and I'm I don't think that I'm
popping up surprises here is the shift
to containers cuz containers tend to be
especially when you're using the
industry standard which is Kubernetes
right right now. Don't think that I'm
going to offend anyone by saying that.
Kubernetes is the industry standard with
containers on top of that. That makes
life easier in terms of multi-cloud and
the way that you work with various
clouds.
Still a lot of enterprises are
struggling with putting their stuff into
let's say container environments. The
reason for that one is that most of the
bigger enterprises have large
environments and these environments are
typically not invented or architected
like microservices environments etc.
These are in some cases really big
monolith applications that you really
would need to re-architect before you
could get it into an architecture that
would allow for microservices and
containers and serverless and other
native stuff.
That's basically also where I usually
come in because you really have to start
thinking about okay, so if I have this
big monolith application and I want it
to run it into cloud. Okay, so first
question is okay, so why would you want
to run it into cloud? Would that make
life easier for your customers? Would
that make life easier for your
administrators? Whatever. So there
should be a business case there. There
should be a use case to start let's say
ripping apart your monolith application
and completely re-architect it so that
it could fit into a multi-cloud
environment or into a cloud environment.
That's one way to look at it and the
other way is that okay, so leave the
applications as they are and just keep
them where they are. Don't touch them.
Don't do anything with them and start
thinking about okay, so maybe this is a
good moment to start thinking about
building new applications greenfield in
a cloud environment. That would still
mean that you will need to map your
current functionality that you have in
your old application and how to map that
into a new development that you're going
to build out. That's something different
than taking the old application and
transitioning it to a new environment.
Which that's a different thing.
So, there are a lot of ways in how to do
a digital transformation because that's
what you're talking about then. We see a
lot of companies really struggling with
digital transformation.
Not just because of technology, but also
because of just do we have the right
people to do this? Do we have the skills
to do this? And if we manage to get our
environments into cloud environment, do
we have the skills and the people to
manage that? Or do we know the companies
that could do that for us?
And if we do so, are we choosing AWS or
are we choosing Azure? For what reason?
So, what would be the best fit for us?
Can we do that? Would that be a
fit for, let's say, all the countries
that we are present in? If we are a
company that works in more than just one
country?
Or do we need to look at, for any
reason, compliance, latency, whatever,
or do we need to look at different
clouds in different regions? What about
disaster recovery? Well, there are so
many reasons that you still have to look
at before you start shifting into a
cloud environment. It's, yeah, it's a
little bit dangerous to say so, maybe,
but I'm still going to say it. The
technology per se is not the issue. It's
everything that comes around it. The
governance, the data.
The technology is usually the easy part.
If you have figured out, cuz okay, so
this is the functionality, these are the
requirements, this is what I need to
build out. I have the people that can do
that. Then the technology is not really
that big of a hurdle anymore. Having
said that, test it, test it, test it.
Keep an eye on security and everything
that comes with it. But technology,
you'll probably be okay to manage that.
It's a lot of stuff that comes with it,
I would say.
You mentioned Kubernetes at the time of
writing your book, which was 2020. The
book is more heavily emphasizing the
VMs,
Yeah. older generation of technology.
One of the selling points of Kubernetes
is it is an interoperability layer and
in context of our discussion, the
enterprise could also run it on their
own machines. Is that the future of
pretty much everything and will
everything now just be lift and shift
and you drop it into whatever managed
Kubernetes cluster meets your needs in
terms of location or cost or
No, indeed. In 2020, that was the idea.
And well, funny enough, we're now in
2023. So, that's only 3 years, but in
cloud terminology, it's almost like
eternity. A lot of already has happened.
So, in the second edition of the book,
that has already been changed. Yes, it
is Kubernetes, but we also see, funny
enough, that we see companies getting
stuff back into on-premises, but do use
cloud technology for that one. AWS
Outposts, Google Anthos, Azure Stack,
all of these technologies that you can
use to run your application, even your
cloud-native applications into your own
data center
using Kubernetes. We also have quite a
number of companies right now that are
starting to look into IoT, a lot more
than they did just a couple of years
ago, using K3s as a lightweight
Kubernetes version to run applications
on top of their IoT stuff. Data
collectors all over the place,
collecting data, shipping it into little
mini containers and shipping it back to
the environments and and running in
cloud for data analysis for or to get AI
on top of that, to get more results or
better results from data.
We've seen that in healthcare already,
that you collect data from scanners,
just scanners like MR or CT or
whatsoever, anonymize the data, then get
it back into the cloud where AI
regenerates the image and figures out,
okay, so these might be spots that a
radiologist might have missed, but AI
recognizes that yeah, well, based on
whatever we already collected in the
past, this might be something that you
want to have a better look at. All these
features or developments, it's growing
tremendously and it's really becoming
massive. And then, public cloud is
really almost essential because it needs
so much power, so much compute power, so
much storage, everything. It needs to be
so scalable. You wouldn't be able to do
that in your on-premises data center
unless you
you get truckloads full of servers every
day in to scale out your environment.
So, you at certain point, there's no
escaping to getting into public cloud.
And then, there's obviously the
development of your applications that
come with it that it's moving it's
changing so so fast. Just taking my
banking applications on my phone again
as an example, I think I get every 2
weeks I get an update with new features
into that application. And that can only
happen if developers have the
possibilities to work on systems that
are scalable. And sure, it all needs to
be secure, it needs to be compliant,
they really need a lot of data to work
with.
So, coming back to your question,
containers, yes, it's still containers,
it's not just containers in the cloud
anymore, it's containers all over. It's
on IoT, it's data collectors, it's
everywhere.
So, it is a technology that is
expanding, it's growing. Yes, I do still
think that Kubernetes is and will be the
industry standard.
That's just a prediction that I don't
think that's anyone would would disagree
with that one. Yeah, it's so it's
containers. I also see a lot of movement
in serverless, event-based
architectures, completely automated.
There's a tremendous growth in that
area. And then, there's data and
security, but that's a completely
different topic, but still data. If I
see the the of data and the growth in
the amount of data that we're collecting
right now as a let's say entire world
community and expect if we expand that
over the years,
yeah, it's going to be huge. It's really
going to be huge.
You mentioned these on-prem hybrid
models such as Anthos. I do want to also
come back to that, but before going in
that direction, I wanted ask you about
another use case. We've talked about
companies want to run the same apps or
services in different places, which may
require using different vendors. Then
you have the best-of-breed solution on a
single vendor. Are there any use cases
you're aware of such as distributed
cluster? I can think of products like
Cassandra where you can span a
distributed database across multiple
regions where you would integrate two
networks from different cloud providers
in order to have
geographic redundancy.
So, what I'm asking about the same app
that the app itself is running on two or
more clouds at once. Is that a thing?
I have to think about a use case.
There's one use case that well, besides
the one use case that probably will come
up in everyone's mind is let's say the
entertainment industry, the Netflix of
this world.
That's an obvious one. There's one other
use case that I can think of and that
that has to do more with the fact that
we that we're living in a world where we
try where we all try to lower our carbon
footprints so that we are working with
that we are building houses that with
that are really efficient energy.
With heat pumps and I know one company I
cannot name unfortunately I cannot name
the name or I cannot say the name, but I
know for one company that we work with
that they have applications to collect
data from the heat pumps and that
actually also push maintenance software
back to the heat pumps that are inside
houses of people. Without them knowing
that this stuff is happening, it is
maintained completely remotely
controlled, maintained from a
centralized application. But that's a
Japanese company, obviously, and that it
means that they have to have that
application, or at least the software
just distributed all over the world from
different places. So, yes, they use
different clouds for that one. The
application, the app itself, is just the
same. Wherever you are, the app works
exactly the same, has the same look and
feel. There's no difference in whether
you have the app in Europe, or in the
US, or in Japan. It's it's completely
same thing, besides the language,
obviously. But to distribute, let's say,
the maintenance data to the heat pumps,
to the equipment in the houses, yeah,
you have to have that really close to
where your customers are, where where
the actual equipment is. And yes, they
are using different data centers for
that one. It's it's GCP, it's AWS, it's
Azure. It's just where it depends where
the data centers are, as close as as
possible to the customers.
The same applies for maintenance of
electrical cars, or EVs. It applies for
a lot of stuff. Televisions, it applies
to really a lot of things.
It also includes for health care.
Happens to be a little bit of my sweet
spot. You want to have AI results to
help radiologists, or doctors, or
whatsoever, in health care, to help them
with results, with diagnostics, you need
exactly the same technology. You have
that data, that data needs to be pretty
close to where actually clinicians are.
Yes, a lot of good companies use
different clouds for that one. Just just
where where the data can be as close as
possible to where the hospitals are, or
health care institutions.
That includes, for instance, the use of
even 5G connections, private 5G, using
technologies like wavelength in AWS to
get services that you run in AWS as
close to the connections, to cut the
bandwidth, or
to to cut the latency to an absolute
minimum.
All these technologies will come down to
basically the same sort of thing to get
the data as close to your customer as
you possibly could get could get it.
And then, the one thing that really is
tricky for that matter is the
synchronization of the data because all
that data needs to be sort of the same
set. I cannot have
completely different data in China than
I Well, maybe a bad example. But, let's
let's put it that way. The data in
Europe and US should be basically the
same data. So, there's That's the
biggest challenge in multi-cloud is
synchronization and keeping your
environments as as synced as much as
possible.
Not only just because of the let's say
the services that you're delivering to
your customers, but also because of the
reasons because of disaster recovery.
For instance, if something fails, you
want to be sure that somewhere your data
is preserved and in the latest version
and you still can rebuild it if really
needed.
I did not come across any events where
something was so heavily destroyed that
you really have to have to get it from a
different region again to build it up.
But yeah, in theory, it is possible.
If I were approaching
application like you've described, I
might pick one of the vendors that I
thought had a good telemetry stack that
could input that could ingest all of the
metrics, store the metrics, provide the
query capability, dashboards, and then
route all the data into that vendor.
Is that a good way to think about the
problem?
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah, absolutely. That is a
good way and most of the public cloud
providers have these networks. They can
do that already. At least the bigger
ones, the major ones, they have these
networks that they can provide the
services around the globe. The only
thing is is that there might be cloud
providers or that are really specialized
that really have a different shader in
in their services. We have customers, I
have customers that are located both in
Japan and Europe and in US. Some of
these customers use F data stacks and
they use for instance Exadata, Oracle
Exadata. Oracle has his own cloud,
Oracle cloud infrastructure. And we see
and that that is also multi-cloud. They
want to have that can be because of a
number of reasons. They want to have the
data
as Oracle data sets, Exadata into Oracle
cloud. There can be a financial benefit
to that one.
Licenses whatsoever.
But there also because they are used to
having that sort of data in specific
formats that they
that they're used to work with. Which is
fine. What we typically do because a lot
of these companies also work with a
major cloud provider like AWS or Azure.
They have the Exadata in OCI and they
have services running in Azure. It can
be workplace services for instance in
AWS where they have development
environments. I actually have one
customer that actually has all three of
them. Has Azure because of the workplace
services. They have AWS for development
and they have OCI for the Exadata stack.
What we try to do is then that this may
sound a little bit complex, but it all
needs to be connected to each other. You
really have to start thinking from a
network perspective and not from the
server or the application layer. No, you
have to start thinking from the network
perspective. Okay, so how do we connect
all these things? In this case, if we
look at the data centers, if we are
lucky, the data centers are situated
close to each other or there might be
even one data center where they both
maybe even three stacks are available.
Or you have to start thinking about meet
me rooms where you have really can
connect the whole thing. You have to
start thinking about the direct
connections that they might have with
Express route or direct connect or
whatsoever, whatever you need. But it
really starts with thinking about okay,
so what are the connections that we need
and not only just connections as such,
but also the speed of the connections,
how much data will flow through it, how
fast does the application need to be for
the for the end customer. And also
there, there's a big difference in the
sort of industry we are in. If you're in
healthcare, applications should be fast
as lightning because a doctor doesn't
have the time to wait minutes for the
results to come back. And the example
that I just mentioned with the
utilities, it might might even be okay
if something takes a little bit longer
than a couple of minutes or even an hour
or whatsoever to get your maintenance
software to equipment in your house.
Nothing will happen if that's a little
bit delayed. So, all these different
parameters you need to take into account
when you start defining and and
architecting your environment and and
especially your cloud environments. And
network, I found this pretty
unbelievable when I started off in
cloud, which is really a long time ago,
but in data centers we used to start
thinking from the networks. The network
was number one, that was your
foundation. And I was surprised to find
out that companies, as soon as they
start moving into cloud, they don't
start thinking about networks, they
start thinking about the applications
and the servers and all that kind of
stuff. Uh-uh. It's the same thing in
cloud. You just have to start thinking
about your networks and your security. I
always stress the fact that whatever you
do, keep security always on top of mind
because if you don't, it's not something
that you can put on on top off later on.
It's it needs to be completely
intrinsic. And for some reason in data
centers, we were used to that kind of
thinking. We had these gates and with uh
badges and no one was able to enter if
they were not allowed to enter. And for
some reason in cloud, yeah, we need to
do something about access management.
Yeah, we need to do something about
security. Start thinking like you would
start thinking in your own data center.
You didn't want anyone to enter your
data center if that person didn't have
anything to look for in that data center
didn't have any business in that data
center. It's the same thing in cloud.
And network-wise, it's exactly the same
thing. Start thinking from your
networks. That's where it starts.
You know, a lot of directions we could
go with this in limited time, but I have
had experience with AWS even networking
between two AWS regions was not
particularly well supported at one time.
I haven't been on AWS in a bit, so that
may have improved. We've been talking
about this idea that you outsource your
computing to somebody who has infinite
compute power, so you don't have to
worry about it. And then you find that
you still are constrained on the network
level looking at a larger topology. What
is the cutoff where you can use the
public internet and just route over that
to where you need to start building
specialized networks and bringing in
Telcos or physical spaces where you
start connecting your network gear in
order to get uh amount of bandwidth you
need.
The answer to that question is actually
quite simple. It starts with what sort
of data are you transporting? Are you
transmitting over over those
connections? If that's private, it's
uh there are two two answers basically.
It's the criticality of your
applications. It's the criticality of
your of your data. And those are the two
main differentiators for having to
decide whether you're going to have to
use private connections or that you can
route it just over the plain internet. I
would not recommend to do that anyway,
by the way.
In the book, I describe two ways, VPNs
and private connections.
The two main drivers are data and the
criticality of your of your application.
And with that last thing, what I do mean
is that there are a lot of quality
attributes that you can use to design
and to architecture your application. An
application that is running production,
that is running sensitive data, and that
needs to be for instance 7 by 24, if
your business is depending on whether
the application is up or down.
If your business is depending on whether
the data is safeguarded, is protected,
and etc., etc., or not, then please
don't go over just just over plain
internet. And just don't do that. And to
be quite honest with you, I hardly can
think of companies that that work with
data and applications
that I would not advise to at least give
it a serious thought about how they
protect their connections and how they
would protect their networks. Yeah, even
not in development. I do see it happen
though, developers just working from
home and just going out on on the
internet and just fiddling around a
little bit with code, and that code
eventually ends up in application code
for their employer, for the for the
companies where they work for, and I
really would go like, "Oh, man, I would
rather have you do that in a protected
environment where I'm sure that data is
not leaked out somewhere. Or maybe it's
not even that you're aware of the fact
that you're working with data that might
be sensitive or that might be useful to
someone that you don't want to have that
data in into their hands." I see a lot
of developers that are simply not aware
of the fact that you're working with
critical stuff. They're working with
sensitive stuff. So, basically, that's
that's where awareness starts. Like,
start thinking, "Is this something that
would harm anyone if it if it drops
somewhere in a public Git repository if
someone started using that?" The matter
of mindset, that's not even technology,
that's just plain mindset. But coming
back to the to the question, companies,
I would always really give it serious
thoughts about how to secure your
connections, what sort of connections
you use, who is allowed on those
connections, who has access, and all
those kind of things. And that's
governance.
Time we have left, we have time for a
couple more questions. I wanted to delve
a little bit into one of the things I
put in our backlog that identity and
access management. Each of the cloud
providers offers their own model for
this. Company that is not all in on one
cloud may have its own identity provider
or run LDAP or Windows directory
internally. And if you're wanting to
deal with multiple cloud services, where
is the source of truth for your
employees' identity and authorization?
And how do that extend onto different
cloud providers without just replicating
or having multiple
conflicting ideas about this?
Well, most enterprises that I work with
still work with active directory. Most
of the enterprises do. Or they have Octa
or something like that. I don't have a
preference for anything. As long as you
are absolutely clear on what is your
single source of identity provision. So,
what is your source of identities? That
should be one source and one source
only. And don't start using Facebook for
that one, please.
I've seen that. I really have seen that.
Oh, yeah, yeah, no, no, our developers
can go in with their Facebook account.
Oh, man, come on. I know you that you
can do that. I know that. So, active
directory, it's still commonly used. And
I'm totally fine with that. It's what I
said. Make sure that that is your one
and only single source of identities.
And that is maintained and managed by
yourselves. Here it comes already. I've
seen companies where directories are
managed by I don't know how many people.
Also, don't do that. Yeah, sure, break
glass accounts, everything, yeah,
something that you all have to have in
place. But your source of identities
should be protected like a vault, really
a vault. And and only a a few people
should be allowed to go into that vault
to make changes to elevate right rights
or whatsoever. That's the basic, really
the core of governance in my world.
Starting from that point, now you want
employees to have access to do different
things on AWS, on Google, but you want
to control that centrally. How do you
extend your
internal identities and authorizations
into granting employees the permissions
to do the work they need to do on the
different cloud services, and yet keep
it under central control, so they don't
now have these distinct identities on
each cloud that are, you know, unmanaged
or you have to manage them multiple
times?
It really should be coming from that one
source of identities with assigned
roles.
And that role can have a definition,
okay, so you're allowed to work in
Google using I am from Google. You're
allowed to work in AWS using AWS
identity and access management, what
whatsoever. But, the role should always
be the same, and that should have the
same definition. And that is managed
centrally. And if a user, and all these
clouds have exactly the same sort of
mechanism to elevate rights if needed.
So, don't go into what I call, again,
I've seen companies where developers
have really have god mode almost in AWS
or in Azure. They can do anything. So,
it already starts with separation of
duties, and it starts with setting up
your clouds in such a way that they only
can access those parts that they really
should be access have access to. And
that that has to do with the way how you
set up your VPCs and everything that is
inside the VPCs, your resources. So,
it's also matter of controlling the
resource management itself on the on the
resource itself. And then there is the
identity, and what I describe in the
book is that everything is an identity.
If you perceive everything as an
identity, including servers, including
services, including users, etc., then
start think about, okay, so if
everything is an identity, every
identity should have a role, and every
role should have certain tasks or
allowances or whatever. That's basically
what our back model does. You should
have that in place and then you can
connect to from your single source of
identities, you can connect to Google I
am, you can connect to Azure AD, you can
connect to AWS I am or have a more
agnostic platform in terms of Octa for
instance that manage it for you, which
is fine as well.
I have a quite a number of customers
that work with Octa for that matter just
as a centralized management platform,
which is absolutely good.
The last thing I want to cover is the
space that you mentioned earlier that
includes outpost Google Anthos in which
it blurs the distinction between
what is really a cloud service and who
owns the resources.
Explain what this space is about, what
problem it's trying to solve and what
some of the offerings are doing in that
area.
It solves two main problems. The first
issue that it solves is that you have
your data as close to your customers or
to your developers as it as it can be
because you're running the stuff really
in your own data center, but you still
want to use the cloud services. You
still want to be able to work from that
one cloud console or with the one CLI
that you're using or SDK or whatever.
That is what all these offerings provide
you. So you're getting an extension of
their public cloud in your own data
center.
So it gives you a feeling that might
might not be the right word, but at
least a lot of companies
choose for that form because they have
it gives them the ability to have it all
under their own control. They have the
machines sitting right next to them sort
of
and they still can work as they would
work in the cloud, in the real cloud, in
the public cloud. So that's number one.
So having the data, your applications
really sitting next to you on your in
your own environment.
That is one of the reasons I think one
of the main reasons to have these
propositions just to have applications
and data in a non-premises setting but
still be able to use cloud services as
you would use them in the public cloud.
So, that's the main reason for for
having these propositions and I also see
it happening for companies that have
distributed applications and distributed
data that they have at the customer's
sites. So, again, it's it's a matter of
limiting the latency of applications and
and data communication as much as they
can. So, it's basically there are a
couple of reasons. So, it's compliancy
and security. So, there might be a
reason to have the data on your own data
center floor. There might be a reason
for latency to cut down latency to have
it really close to your customers and
then but still all these propositions
come with the fact that
you could still work with these
on-premises stacks as you would work in
the public cloud with exactly the same
services, which is not completely true
by the way because if you look at the
public cloud services for instance in
Google Cloud, it's not going to work
exactly the same on Anthos. So, there
are differences. Azure Stack, a lot of
services that you will have in Azure are
available in Azure Stack. The same
applies for AWS Outposts. A lot of
services that you have in AWS are
available in Outposts. But then again,
not in every region and not every
service is available. So, also here you
would really have to think about, "Okay,
so what am I going to use it for? What
service do I need? And does it fit then?
Is it a good fit?"
And coming back to containers, most of
these services do support in the
meantime container services. In AWS, we
have a EKS, AKS in Azure. Anthos is
basically invented to run containers
on-premises. So, there we go again.
Containers is still probably one of the
main solutions for the future.
Within Kubernetes, you have the concept
of the cluster auto scaling or the
cluster itself can either acquire more
nodes or VMs or release them based on
the overall workload of the cluster.
Would any of these hybrid solutions
support the ability either run the
managed cluster and the enterprise would
supply some of the nodes to auto scale
or the reverse where
you have the Kubernetes running on the
enterprises assets and it could pull in
auto scale resources from the cloud or
however you want to mix and match it. Is
that a use case for this model?
What I always tell my customers that are
looking into these propositions is that,
okay, you're buying a piece of kit of
hardware that is not as scalable as you
would have it in the public cloud. And
indeed with auto scaling of clusters,
hardware that sits on your floor has a
certain limit. It can only scale to that
what the hardware actually has
available.
Which is different in public cloud. And
here, this is the interesting part of it
because a lot of companies say, "Yeah,
but that's good. That's exactly what I
want because I know them for sure that
it does not go beyond the boundaries
that I have. So, it can scale up until
these limits and that's it. So, I have
also with that, I have full control
about my financials for that matter. I
know exactly it's going to cost me this
and nothing more than that. If you run
your auto scale extending into public
cloud, and please make sure that you
have these parameters set very really
well. Again, this is more the topic for
FinOps, financial operations,
be sure that you have set limits,
parameters that control your costs in
cloud. Auto scaling is a wonderful
feature. You also have to manage that.
Auto scaling does not mean that you do
not have to manage it anymore. You still
have to manage
to what extent is is something allowed
to scale to. You need to have
thresholds. Cloud providers, they will
tell you that yes, sure, and and and I
believe them, absolutely I believe them.
But cloud providers will tell you,
"Okay, so we are you can auto scale,
it's almost infinite, whatever you
want." And they also will tell you, "But
please be aware that nothing comes for
free, basically. So, there will be a
bill at the end of the month that
specifies, "Okay, so this is what you
have been using in the cloud." And they
will also provide you with services to
control those costs. All these cloud
providers do that.
But there's still it's your
responsibility as a customer that uses
the stuff. And the same applies I always
have I have this one slide in my deck
that is basically a toolkit. Cloud
provider is basically a toolkit. They
have all the services of the world, and
you can build the most wonderful things
with it. It's scalable, it's absolutely
scalable to whatever you want. They have
all the security in the world available
at your fingertips, and they need to be
secure. There is no way that they cannot
be secure because they run thousands of
customers on their platforms. If they
are not secure, they're out of business
within before you know it. That does not
mean that responsibility for using these
services lies with the providers. The
responsibility lies with you to use
these tools. They have the tools.
You are the one that decides to use
them. That applies to auto scaling, even
with things like serverless options with
event-driven architectures that really
are depending on scale because
event-driven, if you run a web
and that hits its maximum at Christmas
time when everyone does does their
shopping, you do not want to have they
hit the limits within, let's say, the
first hour of the sales. Event-driven,
as soon as sales hit, then you really
want to have it scaled. But still, have
boundaries, have thresholds in place,
have parameters in place that will allow
you to control the whole thing. It
sounds like the obvious thing, but still
I notice that it's something that you
did not have to have to worry about when
you were still in the old data center
because it only could go as far as it as
as it went. The hardware would allow you
to do as much as it could do and that
was it. In cloud with auto scaling if
you do not set thresholds and I hardly
can imagine that anyone would not set a
threshold to to
to their environments or budget alerts
or whatever you want to call it. But
still you have to think about, okay, if
I use the cloud, what are the
boundaries, what are the definitions,
what are the parameters, how do I scale,
to what extent do I scale, what do I
use, for what reason do I use it, do I
really need to use it? Everything coming
back to the phrase that I used before,
start thinking of the cloud as if it was
your own data center still. It comes
with a lot of benefits
but it does not mean that you do not
have to think of the let's say the basic
stuff that you would have to think about
if you were setting up your own data
center.
That's what I call base ops and in the
book it's called base ops, basic
operations, and that's not really that
different much different from let's say
the basic operations that we would have
in the old fashioned data centers.
If you could pick any topic we've
discussed where you think the world has
not reached an equilibrium or end point,
where do you see that going in the next
3 years?
I would pick two topics and I already
mentioned them. The first one is
security. I see so much wrong stuff
happening in cloud in terms of security
and that's because
again, it's all about governance and
control. The amounts of data are beyond
my expectations that I had 10 years ago
for instance and it's growing. It's
growing awfully fast. If I look at my
own house,
almost everything is connected to except
for my coffee machine, that's the one
thing that is not connected to the
internet right now, but almost
everything is connected to the internet
and it actually collects data. It
collects a lot of data. It collects data
about my energy levels, it collects data
about the life cycle of my lamps for
even. All that stuff. So, that's number
one. But, I also have to be I have
cameras, surveillance cameras on my
house, collects data. The one thing that
I need to be aware of is that and that
all comes and is all collected and is
ending up somewhere in a cloud. I don't
know because I'm buying it as a service
or I don't know exactly in what cloud it
ends up, but I know one thing that I
need to be aware of the fact that it is
sending data to some cloud by the guys
that actually provide me the services. I
need to be aware of that and I need also
need to be aware of that that as soon as
anyone hacks into my camera, they're
basically on my network and they're they
can hop onto almost anything. Exactly
the same thing for companies. I have
witnessed that audits with let's say an
ethical hacker that actually went to the
entrance of a company with the uh what
do you call it? The bar that goes up
when you as soon as you you enter the
park drive and the bar
goes up. That was connected to a system
that was connected to the internet. And
I witnessed the fact that an ethical
hacker actually went into that system
and was able to hack or to go into the
database with all the HR data. It's all
connected. So, that's number one. Number
two is is financials. Already I
mentioned that a couple of minutes ago.
Companies that come with me with the
question or with the assignment, yeah,
we want to go into cloud because
probably it's going to be a lot of
cheaper if we move our stuff into cloud.
If that's your sole reason to go into
cloud, I'm not going to help you with
that one because it will certainly end
up in a in a big disappointment. If you
want to go into cloud because your
customers demand new applications, new
features, you want to be able to develop
faster, you want to use services that
are available in the cloud that can help
grow your business,
I'm your man. I can help you with that
one.
If you want to spend $1 million in
cloud, I'm fully okay with that as long
as you make a $101 million back from the
cloud again with your business by using
the services.
That should be your motivation to move
into new technology. So, security,
financials.
I do want to point listeners toward a
earlier episode we did, shall put in the
show notes, about FinOps, which goes
into more detail about some of the
topics you touched on. To wrap up, I
have the 2020 edition of your book. Is
that the first edition?
That's the first edition.
Okay.
The second edition just came out 2 weeks
ago.
Okay. And where is that available?
Uh that's available on amazon.com.
Same publisher, Packt. Multi-cloud
strategy for cloud architects.
Uh that's a completely revised edition.
Includes base off FinOps, DevSecOps, but
it also includes OCI and a little bit of
Alibaba Cloud even in this edition.
Anywhere else on the internet where
you'd like listeners to find you?
My LinkedIn profile is open to anyone. I
am on Twitter. I'm not really active on
Twitter right now. I also have an
account on Mastodon and my own website,
yeronmeller.net.
That's where I keep where I write the
blogs and all that kind of thing
all that kind of things and where you
also will find the books.
Yeron, thank you so much for speaking to
Software Engineering Radio.
Thank you for having me.
This has been Robert Blumen. Thank you
for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at SE-Radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
SE-Radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.